Robert Anderson Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Robert Anderson Papers 1819-1948 (bulk 1836-1870)
MSS10967
Anderson, Robert, 1805-1871
5,000 items 19 containers plus 1 oversize 5 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States Army officer. Correspondence, letterbooks, printed material, writings, and official documents relating to Anderson’s military duty in the Black Hawk War, Mexican War, and Civil War, and to his writings on coast defense, ordnance, and artillery tactics. Includes papers of his daughter, Eba Anderson Lawton, historian and biographer of her father.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Anderson, Larz, 1866-1937--Correspondence.; Anderson, Robert, 1805-1871.; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867--Correspondence.; Barnum, P. T. (Phineas Taylor), 1810-1891--Correspondence.; Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893--Correspondence.; Clinch, Duncan Lamont, 1787-1849--Correspondence.; Crawford, Samuel Wylie, 1829-1892--Correspondence.; Crittenden, John J. (John Jordan), 1787-1863--Correspondence.; Dix, John A. (John Adams), 1798-1879--Correspondence.; Doubleday, Abner, 1819-1893--Correspondence.; Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893--Correspondence.; Holt, Joseph, 1807-1894--Correspondence.; Lawton, Eba Anderson, d. 1919. Eba Anderson Lawton papers.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865--Correspondence.; Pickens, F. W. (Francis Wilkinson), 1805-1869--Correspondence.; Scott, Winfield, 1786-1866--Correspondence.; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891--Correspondence.; Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1814-1869--Correspondence.; Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Army --Artillery.; United States. Army --History.; United States. Army --Ordnance and ordnance stores.
Subjects
Black Hawk War, 1832.; Coast defenses--United States.; Mexican War, 1846-1848.
Places
Fort Sumter (Charleston, S.C.); South Carolina--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.
Occupations
Army officers.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Robert Anderson, United States Army officer, were given to the Library of Congress by Maria and Sophie Anderson in 1922. Additional material was transferred from the Library of Congress Archives in 1989.
Additional Guides
A card index of correspondents in the Anderson Papers is available for use in the Manuscript Division Reading Room.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Robert Anderson are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1805, June 14 Born, Louisville, Ky.
1821-1825 Cadet, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y.
1825 Second lieutenant, Third Artillery
1825-1826 Secretary to United States minister to Colombia
1826-1828 In garrison, Ft. Monroe, Va.
1828-1832 On ordnance duty
1832 Served in the Black Hawk War
1834 At Fort Constitution, N.H.
1835-1837 At United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y.
1837-1838 In the Florida War
1838 Aide-de-camp to General Winfield Scott
1838-1841 Assistant adjutant general, Eastern Department
1841-1843 On Board of Officers to examine his "Instruction for Field Artillery"
1845-1846 In garrison, Fort Moultrie, S.C.
1847 Served in Mexican War
1848-1853 In garrison, Fort Preble, Me.
1853-1854 Governor, United States Branch Military Asylum, Harrisburg, Ky.
1855-1859 Inspector of Iron Work, Trenton, N.J.
1860-1861 In command, Defences of Charleston, S.C.
1861 In command, Department of Kentucky and the Cumberland
1863 In command, Fort Adams, R.I.
1865 Raised the flag at Fort Sumter, S.C.
1871 Died, Nice, France
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Robert Anderson (1805-1871) span the years 1819-1948, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1836-1870. Included in the collection are correspondence and letterbooks, printed matter, drafts of writings, and official documents. Part of the material relates to Anderson's military duty in the Black Hawk War and Mexican War and to his writings on coast defense, ordnance, and artillery tactics. Chief interest centers in his prominent role at the outbreak of the Civil War, when he was commander of the Union garrison during the bombardment of Fort Sumter. Also in the collection are the papers of Anderson's daughter, Eba Anderson Lawton, historian and biographer of her father.
Correspondents include Larz Anderson, A. D. Bache, P. T. Barnum, G. T. Beauregard, Duncan Lamont Clinch, Samuel Wylie Crawford, John J. Crittenden, John A. Dix, Abner Doubleday, Hamilton Fish, Joseph Holt, Abraham Lincoln, F. W. Pickens, Winfield Scott, William T. Sherman, Edwin McMasters Stanton, and Charles Sumner.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
General Correspondence, 1819-1870
Miscellany, 1838-1911
Eba Anderson Lawton Papers, 1833-1919
Addition, 1861-1948
Oversize
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm78010967
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1819-1870 (Box 1-17)
  Bound volumes of correspondence, including a journal of 1838-1841, followed by a letterbook and loose correspondence.
  Bound volumes of correspondence are arranged chronologically.
  - Includes journal for 1838-1841, 13 Dec. 1819-5 Mar. 1836, 1838-1841 (Box 1)
  - 9 Mar. 1836-21 Sept. 1839 (Box 2)
  - 23 Sept. 1839-29 Mar. 1842 (Box 3)
  - 30 Mar. 1842-7 Feb. 1846 (Box 4)
  - 9 Feb. 1846-1 Apr. 1847 (Box 5)
  - 4 Apr. 1847-19 Sept. 1853 (Box 6)
  - 26 Sept. 1853-12 Nov. 1859 (Box 7)
  - 15 Nov. 1859-28 Dec. 1860 (Box 8)
  - 29 Dec. 1860-10 Jan. 1861 (Box 9)
  - 11 Jan. 1861-12 Feb. 1861 (Box 10)
  - 13 Feb.-11 Apr. 1861 (Box 11)
  - 12 Apr.-17 May 1861 (Box 12)
  - 18 May-24 Aug. 1861 (Box 13)
  - 25 Aug. 1861-7 Jan. 1862 (Box 14)
  - 9 Jan. 1862-12 May 1864 (Box 15)
  - 14 May 1864-29 Aug. 1870, undated (Box 16)
  - Letterbook of correspondence written from Trenton, N. J., 8 Jan. 1856-24 Oct. 1859 (Box 17)
  - Letters (Box 17)
    - To Nathaniel Silsbee, 22 June 1858 (Box 17)
    - To Nathaniel Silsbee, 9 Dec. 1859 (Box 17)
    - To Nathaniel Silsbee, 26 Jan. 1861 (Box 17)
    - To Lloyd Tilghman, 20 Mar. 1861 (Box 17)
    - To Nathaniel Silsbee, 30 May 1861 (Box 17)
- Miscellany, 1838-1911 (Box 17-18)
  Presentation copies of books, clippings and other printed matter, commissions, and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material.
  - Book of clippings about Anderson, including letters from authors who dedicated hymns and poems to Anderson, 2 Jan. 1861-Oct. 1871 (Box 17)
  - Commissions and certificates See Oversize (Box 17)
  - Discharge certificate of Jean Botzy, First Regiment de Chasseurs d'Afrique, 31 Dec. 1838 (Box 17)
  - "Evolutions of Batteries," 1840, published in 1860 by United States War Department, Evolutions of Field Batteries of Artillery, 1840; 1860 (Box 17)
  - "Instruction for Siege, Garrison, & Sea Coast Artillery," including draft of "Evolutions of Field Batteries of Artillery," 1843 (Box 17)
  - Photolitho facsimile of telegram, Anderson to Simon Cameron, 18 Apr. 1861 (Box 17)
  - Presentation volumes (Box 17)
    - Soldier and Pioneer: a Biographical Sketch of Lt. Col. Richard C. Anderson of the Continental Army by E. L. Anderson (New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1879. 63 pp.) (Box 17)
    - Major Robert Anderson and Fort Sumter 1861, by Eba Anderson Lawton (New York: Knickerbacker Press, 1911. 19 pp.) (Box 17)
    - The Political Conspiracies Preceding the Rebellion or The True Stories of Sumter and Pickens, by Thomas M. Anderson (New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1882. 100 pp.) (Box 17)
    - Within Fort Sumter by One of the Company (New York: N. Tibbals & Co., 1861. 72 pp.) (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and printed matter (Box 18)
    - Activities of Eba Anderson Lawton (daughter) (Box 18)
    - Attack on Fort Sumter, S.C. (Box 18)
- Eba Anderson Lawton Papers, 1833-1919 (Box 19)
  Mainly letters received by Lawton regarding Robert Anderson.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Letters received by Lawton pertaining to a memorial to Robert Anderson, the Fort Sumter, S.C., flag controversy, and the publication of "The History of the Soldier's Home," 1833-1919 (Box 19)
- Addition, 1861-1948 (Box 19)
  Photocopies of annotated drawing by Truman Seymour of Cummings Point near Fort Sumter, S.C.
  - Annotated drawing of Cummings Point near Fort Sumter, S.C., by Truman Seymour, negative and positive photocopies, 1861, 1948 (Box 19)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  Commissions and certificates.
  Described according to the series and container from which it was removed.
  - Commissions and certificates (Container 17) (Box OV 1)